Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Library Oral History Collection AD.MC.023
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Interview with Matthew Silverstein by Ilka Datig (40:00), 11 May 2014; ADMC023_ref17; 40 minutes; 107.1 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref17)
  In this interview, Silverstein discusses his early years as the first standing faculty member hired at NYU Abu Dhabi, with special interest on the pedagogical, physical, and intellectual challenges of setting up the University. While recounting the dilapidated facilities and self-aggrandizing students with humor Silverstein emphasizes the importance and intimacy of relationships between faculty and with students during the early days. Silverstein discusses the challenges teaching such small class sizes and of building a philosophy program without the capacity for long term residencies. The second half of the interview discusses the press coverage of labor practices during the final days of Saadiyat campus construction. While acknowledging the real harm done, Silverstein critiques the approach of press coverage at the time of recording. The interview concludes with Silverstein's message for future students, faculty, and staff: we did our best.
- Interview with John Sexton by Ilka Datig (60:00), 24 May 2014; ADMC023_ref18; 1 hours; 160.52 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref18)
  Video-recorded session with John Sexton, President of New York University, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  John begins this interview by describing the evolution of the Global Network University (GNU) from GNU 1.0 which saw the incorporation of sites like NYU Madrid and Paris, through GNU 5.0 which he sees as the full integration of the NYU organic circulatory system, as a connected community rather than an accumulation of multinational sites. He describes his first majlis meeting with Crown Prince Sheikh Mohamed bin Zayed which lasted much longer than the planned 15 minutes, and began the inception of NYU Abu Dhabi as a full portal campus rather than a study away site. Noteworthy is the importance of the NYU Abu Dhabi Institute and the Sheikh Mohamed bin Zayed Scholars Program to the development of the institution in Abu Dhabi. John describes the Institute as a program of conferences which ultimately stimulated intellectual life in the Abu Dhabi community and gave world-class academics an introduction to the city. The latter led to the local community's trust in the NYUAD project and illustrated the team's commitment to the success of the institution. He touches on memorable points like navigating cultural difference, the first Candidate Weekend, and the changing nature of meetings with His Highness Sheikh Mohamed and Albert Bloom, the first Vice-Chancellor of NYUAD.
  [*Split into two separate interviews, to facilitate a break.]
- Interview with PJ Henry by Ilka Datig (52:00), 25 May 2014; ADMC023_ref19; 52 minutes; 144.92 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref19)
  Video-recorded session with Associate Professor of Psychology PJ Henry by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this interview, Associate Professor PJ Henry recounts his journey coming to work at NYU Abu Dhabi. Focusing on his initial trepidation at the great risk of joining the NYUAD experiment, Henry shares how he fell in love with the school's vision, and uprooted the lives of him and his partner to be a part of it. He discusses challenges adjusting to the smaller, more relational teaching environment, conducting psychological research in the UAE, and adapting to the rapidly evolving institutional environment. Henry traces how he has grown as an instructor through several key moments in his first few classes and looks to the future of what NYUAD can become in light of his experience.
- Interview with Yousif Asfour by Ilka Datig (20:00), 23 Jun 2014; ADMC023_ref20; 20 minutes; 53.97 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref20)
  Video-recorded session with Yousif Asfour, former Chief Information Officer then Associate Vice President for Strategic Initiatives, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Yousif Asfour, who began his journey with NYU Abu Dhabi as Chief Information Officer, talks about his role in getting the University off the ground in its early stages. He discusses extensively the interface between NYU Abu Dhabi and NYU in New York - the assuredness of building off their model and the challenges of modifying that model to the Abu Dhabi context, for example with networking, which is more difficult and expensive in the UAE. He also mentions the challenges of working two shifts, one in the morning with the Abu Dhabi team, then at night with his New York contacts. Yousif talks about the obstacles with the establishment of the campus which included problems with contractors, setting up the IT infrastructure and negotiating with the government with regard to academic freedom. The IT system was the main focus of his responsibilities including the recruitment of staff, and setting up operations at the Downtown Campus and the new Saadiyat Campus.
- Interview with Praveen Kumar by Ilka Datig (45:00), 24 Jun 2014; ADMC023_ref22; 45 minutes; 123.14 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref22)
  Video-recorded session with Praveen Kumar, Associate Project Director for Planning, Delivery, and Transition for the Saadiyat Campus, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  In this interview, Praveen Kumar shares anecdotes from his time as the Project Director of Planning, Delivery and Transition to the Saadiyat Campus. While skeptical about branching out from his corporate commercial environment, Kumar recounts how he came to lead the provision of NYU Abu Dhabi's physical spaces. From setting up the Center for Science and Engineering in Mussafah to the delivery of the Saadiyat campus, Kumar traces his journey with the University, focusing on the technical challenges overcome, and the relationships forged. Kumar in particular highlights his friendships with Michael Davis and Hilary Ballon as central to his relationship with NYU Abu Dhabi. Proud of the last five years, Kumar trusts his personal and professional investment in NYU Abu Dhabi will yield transformative dividends.
- Interview with Hilary Ballon by Ilka Datig (43:00), 28 Sep 2014; ADMC023_ref23; 43 minutes; 114.09 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref23)
  Video-recorded session with Hilary Ballon, former Deputy Vice Chancellor of NYU Abu Dhabi, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Hilary reflects on her role in the conceptualisation and development of NYU Abu Dhabi as a pioneer of the institution. The inception of the university was based on core principles which included the fostering of an organic connection between the New York and Abu Dhabi campuses, becoming a leader of university education in the region, and forging a deep connection with the Abu Dhabi community. Hilary describes the 'giant leaps' of constructing the Downtown Campus, and later the Saadiyat campus, both of which signified the importance of growth, change and adaptability to the life of NYU Abu Dhabi. Notable challenges included the initial recruitment of impressive and qualified faculty to this startup university, as well as making strong connections with the Emirati community. Both of these hurdles were quickly overcome as world-class faculty became a magnet for others, and the early participants of the Sheikh Mohamed bin Zayed Scholars Program became ambassadors for the University. Hilary fondly remembers her first Candidate Weekend, with speeches by John Sexton and a first cohort that was a microcosm of the world. Her interview ends with a look forward to the growth of the community in the years to come, shaping NYU and Abu Dhabi.
- Interview with Jennifer Gerdes by Ilka Datig (30:00), 30 Sep 2014; ADMC023_ref25; 30:05 minutes; 94.8 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref25)
  Jennifer reflects on her time at NYU Abu Dhabi which started with her position as an academic coach to the first cohort of students in 2010. She remembers her initial impression of Abu Dhabi which include remarks on the weather, the nightlife, and her first experience with Ramadan. As part of the first set of staff at the institution, Jennifer was part of a small dedicated team which led a small community who all lived together in Sama Tower. One challenge of her position was creating a balance between professional boundaries and tight-knit relationships with the students, as she was so close in age to them.
- Interview with Tamu Al-Islam by Ilka Datig (40:00), 1 Oct 2014; ADMC023_ref26; 40 minutes; 108.37 Gigabytes (Object ADMC023_ref26)
  Video-recorded session with Tamu Al-Islam, former Director of Human Resources Services, Strategy and Engagement, by Ilka Datig, former Reference and Research Librarian, NYUAD Library.
  Tamu Al-Islam describes her journey from the administration of NYU, in New York, to NYUAD, as the latter was conceptualised. Her introduction to NYU's initial interest in Abu Dhabi was through the Sheikh Mohamed Bin Zayed Scholars Program which she helped to bring to its current level of prestige. Tamu talks of the early days of the institution when the support within the team was integral to maintaining focus and camaraderie, as well as beginning to understand and experience the city. Points of contention among the team included dealing with the lack of infrastructure, becoming acquainted with local practices different to one's own and the relationship between NYU and the Abu Dhabi campus. Tamu also refers extensively to the growth of NYU Abu Dhabi from what she calls a startup to its stage in 2014, moving to the Downtown Campus, the interaction of students and faculty, growing school population and substantial academic preparation which has contributed to the continued development of the school.